[Music]
Stanford
University okay let's uh let's go back
to I'm going to try to we've done this
before incidentally but uh you know
there's only so much physics out there
and I can't uh keep making it up fast
enough
to uh I wish I could but I can't when I
was younger I
could so we're going to do things that
uh we've done
before all right let's go back to what
we learned about the geometry
of a black hole near the Horizon near
the Horizon we found out that it was
just pretty much good old flat
SpaceTime uh approximately very very
close to the Horizon and we described it
by a particular metric
for this purpose we we started of course
with the good old Schwarz Shield metric
but we made a bunch of changes of
variables in particular instead of the
Schwarz Shield coordinate R there's
never enough ink here instead of the
Schwarz Shield coordinate r that goes
into the Schwarz Shield metric in the
usual
way we replaced it
oh good we replaced it by another
variable which was actually the proper
distance from The Horizon R is not the
proper distance from The
Horizon but row
is that's its definition that's the
definition of row proper distance from
The Horizon and I won't bother writing
down the relationship between them not
not terribly important to know but Row
one thing is important when
at the point when R is equal to 2
mg that's the Schwarz Shield radius
that's the point where the Horizon is at
that point row is equal to zero proper
distance from The
Horizon we also made another change of
variables
Omega which is a Time
variable was equal and it's a
dimensionless Time variable is equal to
the SCH Shield Time ided 4
mg so roughly speaking oh in every place
here C is equal to
one C is equal to
one roughly what Omega is time and
length are measured in the same units
when C is equal to 1 2 mg is The schwar
Shield radius of the black hole so apart
from a factor of two Omega is time
measured in units of The schwar Shield
radius so that's what Omega is and
that's why it's Dimension list because
it's a ratio of uh things time divided
by the Schwarz field radius and when we
did that we went to the little exercise
was a number of steps more steps than I
really like to do but nevertheless we
did it and we found out that near the
Horizon of the black hole the we call it
the near Horizon
geometry that
the proper
distance was
equal to minus Row squar The Omega squar
I could write this in terms of proper
time the difference between proper
distance squared and proper time squar
is just you change the sign you can
write D squ and put a plus sign here the
Omega squar plus d row
squ and then there was another piece
coming from angles on the horizon but
I'm not terribly interested in that I'm
interested in distance from The Horizon
and
time a two-dimensional picture of the
black hole just time and distance from
the black hole okay this is what the
metric is
like and then I pointed out to you that
this metric is very very similar to the
metric of ordinary flat space
conventional flat space the surface of
this um table here in polar
coordinates and polar
coordinates we would ordinarily
write I don't want to write it here
because I don't want to confuse it with
this but ordinarily in polar
coordinates Theta row we would write
that DS s is equal to Row 2 D theta
squar plus d r s so they look very
similar to each
other the only difference is this minus
sign and Omega is analogous to Theta
it's a hyperbolic
angle just to finish yeah all right
that's that's good that's um
that's this is flat space ordinary flat
space this happens to be nothing but
ordinary flat space time in a kind of
polar coordinate uh reference
frame everybody remember
this and Omega is T over 4
mg
now this is the metric
close to the black hole Horizon we draw
a picture of this this is just flat
space in polar coordinates
so it looks something like
this Omega is an kind of hyperbolic
angle
variable which way down in the remote
past Omega is equal to minus infinity
way up here Omega is equal to plus
infinity and
row lines of constant row are just
hyperbolas which look like this
the F and here's the Horizon right over
here is the horizon or right over there
if we come in along a line of constant
Omega fixed time that point right over
there is R = 2 mg it's row equals z but
it's Ral 2 mg so that's what we set up
last time we also said that the Horizon
of the black hole well the general
Horizon The Horizon there's two Notions
of horizon
incidentally one is called the bifurcate
Horizon I'll tell you the words the
bifurcate Horizon is simply this point
over here and the by I don't know what
fkit means but by means two and the two
are the intersection of these two light
cones here that's called the bifurcate
Horizon but there's another notion of
horizon the other notion of horizon
horon is a more physically interesting
one it's this whole lightlike surface
here why is that interesting well if
somebody gets stuck behind that
lightlike surface they cannot send a
message to the outside they cannot send
a message out beyond that lightlike
surface so this is a kind of Horizon and
once you're behind it you can't get any
information out to distance is beyond
the uh Ral 2m or row equal Ral 2m or row
greater than zero okay so that's that's
the geometry of the near
Horizon what about when we go very very
far from the black hole when we go very
far from the black hole we see also it
looks like space time it looks like flat
space time but here's the metric that we
would see we take the Schwarz Shield
metric the good old schwar Shield metric
trick let's write it down D s^2 is equal
to 1 - 2 mg /
R dt^
2 + 1/ 1 - 2 mg /
R the R 2 and now we go far from the
black hole which means R very large what
happens to this when R is very large it
this is dt^ 2 excuse me it just becomes
dt^ 2 plus or minus the T ^2 plus the R
okay R and row far from the black hole R
and row are the same thing once you're
way far away from the black hole the
proper distance to the black hole is
approximately just
R it's only near the black hole that R
and row are very different from each
other but when you're far from the black
hole radius is just radius distance from
The Horizon is basically the same as it
would be in flat space so far from the
black hole row and R are basically the
same
thing this Factor here is not
interesting it goes to one this Factor
down here also goes to one and we just
get minus the t^2 plus the R 2 all right
so far from the black hole then the s s
is minus Row 2
but let's
write sorry not minus row s excuse me I
just want to write dt^ 2 I just want to
write dt^ 2 because there is no
interesting Factor so what is dt^ 2 dt^
2 is 16 m^2 G ^2 D Omega
2 what I've done here is just multiply
by 4 mg so that Omega
so that
t is equal to 4
mg *
Omega that's this piece
here and then the other piece is just
plus d r^
s the d r squared is just this over here
making use of the fact that row and R
are the same thing far from the black
hole so look what's happening that near
the black
hole the only difference the only
interesting difference between these two
is not in the D squ term but it's in the
time term Omega is a kind of time it's
related to time through this equation
over here and on the one hand near the
black hole there's a factor row squared
when row is very very small it means
that time runs very very slowly very
near the Horizon of the black hole there
is very little proper time in any
appreciable D Omega but far from the
black
hole this is what the formula says okay
this is curious what's going on how do
we think about this what kind of
geometry it's it's a little hard to
Envision in fact it's quite hard to
Envision but as you move away from the
Horizon of the black hole this here
thing goes to this
thing let me give you I'll try to give
you the
best picture I can of what this geometry
is
like yeah
minus all
right let's come over to here to this
picture over
here it's much easier to
understand space than it is space time
so let's come back to this picture and
now imagine a geometry which has the
following
property near the origin it looks like
Row 2 D Theta 2 + d^ 2 but far from the
origin it looks like instead of row s
let's just say 16 m^2 g^
2 uh D theta squ plus d
s very similar to what's going on over
here except we're not dealing with
SpaceTime we're dealing with just
ordinary space what kind of geometry is
this so let me show you what it looks
like can you uh can you guess what it
looks
like this
is I'll show you near the origin it
looks like polar
coordinates let me draw this plane on
its Edge like
this here's this plane drawn Edge
on as I go around Theta I just go around
here near the origin it looks like the
plane
but now as I move away from the
origin what happens look at it instead
of having this row squared here we just
get a constant squared the meaning of
that is that the distance around
Theta between two neighboring values of
theta instead of depending on row just
becomes constant becomes 16 m^2 g^ 2
I'll show you what it looks like it
looks like a cigar it looks like a
geometry that looks like this
this where the distance around the cigar
at this end
here is well Theta goes from 0 to 2
pi so the distance around the whole
cigar in this direction the cigar band
is 4
mg times 2
pi Theta goes from 0er to 2 pi as you go
around
and
uh okay so that's that's what's at this
end on the other hand very near the
origin over here it really just does
look like polar coordinates Theta goes
around looks like polar coordinates very
close to the tip of the cigar the cigar
looks
flat any geometry in the vicinity of a
point looks pretty
flat but as you go out and as you move
around
this point
here close to the tip of the cigar this
is the
metric far from the tip of the
cigar the distance around the Theta axis
does not depend on how far away you
are same
here the distance in
Omega when you're far away doesn't
depend on row when you're close in the
distance for a given Omega does depend
on Row the main message here is that
this is a curved space it's a curved
space with a curvature near the
Horizon and how does that curvature
depend on M
and well the distance around this cigar
gets very very big when M andg get big
so when the mass well sorry when the
mass gets big the distance around the
cigar gets big and that means that the
curvature at the tip of the cigar gets
less the bigger the mass is the less
curvature that you have at the tip of
the cigar the less curved it is a small
Mass would look like this highly curved
at this
end this is also true of the Schwarz
Shield black hole highly curved when the
mass is small near the Black Hole uh
tip near the near the Horizon this this
point is the Horizon it becomes it Maps
or becomes this point over
here so you can get some feel for what
this geometry is
like by looking at its ordinary space uh
version but still I think that's not
completely satisfying uh it just is what
it is it is what it is here's the
geometry the coefficient of the Omega
squared varies from Near The Horizon
where it's row
squar to far from The Horizon where it
just becomes a number the number being
16 m^2 g^
that's and that's really all you really
need to know about the black
hole what is
this this this Factor here all right we
look at given angular
separations the fact of in front of the
D Omega squar tells us how much proper
time there is from one Omega let's call
this Omega equals 0 and let's call this
Omega equal
1 near the Horizon very close to the
Horizon where row is very small the
proper time
distance between Omega equal 0 and Omega
equal 1 is very
small okay so near the Horizon As Time
flows as Omega
flows very very little proper time
between neighboring values of
time far from the black
hole neighboring values
simply
have uh times time
differences which are
just this number here which is nothing
but dt^
s okay so clock this is a statement
about clocks clocks far away from the
black hole behave exactly as you would
expect they've read this time here
clock's very close to the black hole
read row time Omega row time Omega Omega
is a kind of time variable but it scales
differently close to the black hole all
right that's that's what a black hole is
like
now
uh again
outside the black hole corresponds to
row greater than zero row greater than
zero is all of these curves here is
rowal 1 rowal 2 Row = 3 Row = 4 that's
outside the black hole anybody who's
stationed at rest outside the black hole
if you could if you were at rest outside
a black hole and just let go you'll
slowly fall toward the black hole if
you're far away if you're very very far
away it'll take a long time but it
doesn't take much effort to stay out of
the black hole you can orbit around the
Black
Hole uh you can just have a little jet
propulsion device that can keep you out
of the black hole and that's moving
along one of these trajectories here
just staying a certain distance away
from the black hole all right on the
other hand once somebody passes through
we'll Now call this the horizon
The Event
Horizon this is the bifet Horizon this
is the Event Horizon once you pass past
the Event Horizon you cannot send a
message to the outside world that's the
character of the black hole that's what
makes it a black
hole great is on that diagram speed of
light is a straight line oh speed of
light radial speed radial light waves
always move on 45° axis in any drawing I
ever draw unless I tell you otherwise
and I may tell you otherwise sometimes
but the speed of light is a 45 degree
line right so a light Ray falling in
that way a light Ray trying to get out
that way but it won't get out so light
rays can fall in but they can't fall
out all right what about the
singularity let's go back to the Schwarz
Shield metric which which I've erased
off the Blackboard someplace and write
it down again and see if we can trace
well first of all let's redraw this
diagram ask a question about the
terminology you're using you're saying
when the light ra Falls in light R
shines into the black hole go ahead what
are you going to ask um cuz does the
light Ray stay at the Horizon and right
across the Horizon of the black hole it
doesn't actually fall we'll
see all well we can answer we can answer
answer that right now here's Bob Bob is
Riding on His
trajectory he's riding on his world line
let's let's move him out a little
bit okay Bob is quite far from the black
hole here
are Omega equals z Omega = 1 Omega = 2
what about the Schwarz Shield time you
know the usual time that Bob measures on
his wristwatch he measures Schwarz
Shield time the T well T and Omega are
basically the same thing except for a
factor of 4 mg so this would be his time
equals zero this would be his time
equals 4 mg this would be his time
equals 8 mg and so forth so riding along
here Bob is looking at his wristwatch
and time is ticking
off there's an infinite number of ticks
along his
trajectory he never falls into the black
hole why not because I tell you he
doesn't fall into the black hole he
stays outside he's orbiting it right so
he stays at a fixed proper distance that
means on a fixed hyperboloid here
here and he looks
back let's draw in Alice now Alice
doesn't have to be Alice Alice could be
a proton it could be a photon it could
be anything falling or moving in this
direction let's say a photon you asked
me about a photon here's a
photon that Photon moves
45° and it sure looks to me like it
passes The Horizon
What About Bob what does Bob say so
Bob's wristwatch reads off
time time Infinity is way way out there
so he looks back from wherever he is
Let's uh get another color onto this
problem
red Bob looks back and he sees the
photon over here why do I say he looks
back
he looks back and he sees the light
coming to him from uh from well light
doesn't usually come
from something yeah
uh strictly speaking Bob can't see this
Photon the photon's going the other way
so let's not make it a photon let's make
it Alice okay it's Alice Alice is
falling
through she's waving her hand as she uh
she falls through and Bob looks at her
let's here's her here's her waves
let's make them closer together she's
waving pretty rapidly along her world
line she's waving hi Bob Bob is looking
back and from this point he sees Alice
over here we all see each
other slightly in the past takes time
light time to get to us so Bob sees
Alice over here next after another
interval of time he sees Alice over here
she's waving a certain number of
times Bob sees Alice wave a few more
times Bob keeps looking
back keeps looking
back and according to him each one of
these measurements each one of these
observations is separated let's say by
one second each one is separated by one
second along this trajectory
here but look what happens he sees sees
fewer and fewer of Alice's Waves per
unit
time eventually as he gets way out there
a huge amount of time of his time
transpires but he only sees one
wave and then as he goes further and
further into the distant future along
his accelerated
trajectory he sees the last wave right
over here but he never sees Alice Cross
The Horizon he cannot see Alice Cross
The Horizon so from his point of view
Alice waves slower and slower and
slower and eventually just comes to a
frozen halt where she appears to be
frozen on just just outside the
Horizon how close to the Horizon well
let's say let's take that point over
here that corresponds to some hyperbola
and that hyperbola tells you how far she
is from The Horizon at that point
so that's Alice yeah so from Bob's
perspective he's going to see Alice in
the exact same place
right he see Alice she's Frozen in the
exact same place right so that means
there are some information that's
being this is a classical picture of the
black hole there's not accounting for
the quantum mechanics of the black hole
right so from a
completely look what would I what would
Bob actually see
imagine Alice you see her wavings
getting slower and slower she's sending
out light waves it's the light waves of
Bob sees how does she send out light
waves she sends out light waves by
taking electric charges and wiggling
them right it's our atoms that do the
wiggling of
course Bob sees Alice's Wiggles of her
charges slow
down what does that say about the light
that Bob sees
at first it's Optical
waves then it becomes
infrared eventually it becomes long
wavelength radio
waves Bob doesn't see Alice anymore but
maybe his uh long wavelength radio can
pick up a few of her waves but then her
wavelengths gets so long or the
frequency gets slow so low that Bob just
doesn't see anything
so really strictly
speaking Alice just Fades away she just
Fades away from uh Bob's point of view
her radiation goes from being Optical
radiation to being thousands of miles
long um INF not infrared but radio waves
and even
longer so Alice Fades
away how about Alice what does she see
you might think maybe that means that
Alice sees Bob speed
up so let's look at what the Alice SE
one quick question before you get to uh
but as Alice is fading away she's also
getting smaller right
moreat if I'm falling onto the Horizon I
slow
down from your point of
view I don't get squashed this way I get
squashed this way
right it's a form of Loren contraction
but uh yes that's what it
sees how about Alice what does Alice
say Alice looks back let's draw let me
draw a little cleaner Alice here now in
green that's this is Alice's clock
Alice's clock doesn't do anything very
special she looks back and sees Bob and
she sees Bob and she sees Bob she sees
even after she passes The Horizon and
she sees
Bob what she sees is Bob accelerate away
from her Bob doesn't disappear from her
uh uh from her
perspective when she crosses the Horizon
not at all what does
happen is she sees him accelerating away
from
her okay so that's what happens to uh
that's Alice's view of things she
doesn't see Bob speed up Bob sees her
slow down but she doesn't see Bob do
anything special when she passes The
Horizon Bob looks perfectly normal she
can send him oh no sorry he can send her
signals he can send her signals from
yeah but she can't send he can send her
signals that goes this way he's sending
her signals but she cannot send him
signals so it's a kind of
one-way barrier The Horizon is oneway
barrier isn't his isn't his light blue
shifted no actually not well I mean as
seen by her as seen by her no as a
matter of fact since he's accelerating
away from her her light is red shifted
his light is red
shifted he's more and more Doppler
shifted toward the red so
no
h she sees him red shifted he SE her red
shifted until she until uh until she
just Fades away okay but it's completely
asymmetric all right that's uh
that's that's the picture of Alice and
Bob uh falling into the black hole that
question yeah does this apply to
gravitons yeah so Alice's gravitons are
never seen by Bob right and her
colleagues right and all the infinite
number of colleagues y
gravitons are just particles like
photons much harder to see but uh much
harder to detect but uh still
conceptually they're just
photons
photons but once Alice falls in the mass
increases so the radius increases once
Alice Falls in what once Alice falls
into the black hole yes like we've
increased the mass of the black Hool so
the radi doesn't
we'll come to that we'll come to the
increase of the mass of the black hole
Yeah we talk about that if the gravitons
can't escape I would think then the then
just like the dark hole black hole not
only dark it would be gravitation free
but
that's
no you don't you don't um feel
gravitational fields because they are
real genuine gravit rabons coming at you
from the earth I thought that was the
the the force uh
the the field that carried the uh uh
gravitational forces virtual
graviton which have no trouble exceeding
the speed of light sorry virtual
gravitons have no trouble exceeding the
speed of
light what's
true is I've been standing here a long
time you can feel my gravitational field
what in a sense you're feeling is the
gravitational field that was created
sometime in the past relative to you now
I move
suddenly the constraints on the speed of
light of gravitons tell you that you
cannot see me move or you won't feel me
move your gravitational field that I
exert on you will not change until light
gets a chance to get to you doesn't that
all it says doesn't that they say that
light in in the gra that gravitational
field moves at the same
speed everything I just said is also
true of
electromagnetic fields if I were highly
charged and you were also highly charged
we might either repel each other or
attract each other he's supposed to
laugh at that but uh right and that
would be a sort of steady state
situation but if I suddenly
moved you would only detect my field
changing by after view at light speed at
light speed I mean but but but you just
said virtual gravitons go at infinite
speed I don't know the distinction
between virtual gravitons and what
you've just described I
guess if it's for not Germain then
that's fine it's not gerain
yeah virtual gravitons you can just
think of as
the
um units of gravitational field which
make up the static gravitational field
of a stationary object right they don't
have to escape from the black hole
they're there they're there they're
they're there
they
okay let's talk about this
puzzle of what you see when you watch
your feet fall through the black hole as
you're
falling everybody always gets confused
about that what happens when I see my do
I see my feet pass through the black
hole
Horizon how can I see my feet pass
through the black hole
Horizon so let's let's set up that
problem Alice is falling into the black
hole here's a feet her feet fall through
first okay she's falling feet feet first
right here's Alice's feet I'm not going
to try to draw feet Yes I will here's
her
feet I can't draw feet okay here's her
feet that's the world line of her left
foot the world line of her head is over
here it follows her in Falls in later so
here's Alice's feet here's Alice's head
Alice is looking at her feet okay so at
this point over here she certainly sees
her feet but she sees her feet over here
she doesn't see her feet at the instant
when she looks at them she sees her feet
slightly in the
past Alice sees her feet from here
there's Alice's foot Alice sees her feet
from
here Alice sees her feet from here and
she sees him from
here yeah right she looks back and sees
the light coming to her from her feet
here's the light coming to her from her
feet along a 45 my 45° angles are not uh
particularly accurate but they're
supposed to be all right so light comes
from here Alice sees it she's wiggling
her toes and her toes are electrically
charged to the ascending light see light
here shees light here shees light here
there's no point at which she doesn't
see her uh at which she doesn't see her
feet of course she doesn't see her feet
from this point and the same
time from this point over here she
doesn't see her foot at that same
instant of time she sees her feet from
slightly in the past so there's nothing
special happens when she passes through
the
Horizon okay now suppose that her head
stays out of the black hole and her feet
which have already passed through too
late our foot has passed through
but she decides at the last minute no I
don't want to go there then what happens
well that's that's bad that's not good
let's see what
happens Alice's
head now whoops now takes
off and separates from her
feet
okay there's no way that she can avoid
her feet being TN off uh by uh by the
acceleration so to keep out of the black
hole she has to accelerate away from her
feet now her feet might get pulled okay
her feet might get
pulled but they can't get pulled fast
enough to keep up with her it looks like
they're keeping up with her but they're
not and the reason is the following as
Bob moves faster and faster in Bob is
accelerating away from the black
hole he's not really accelerating he's
standing still but when you stand still
in a gravitational field it's the same
as
accelerating so Bob is accelerating
away think about this now think Bob
accelerating away and the distance to
Alice or Al Bob and Alice this is now
Bob and Alice Alice is dragging behind
Bob at a fixed distance in your
reference
frame what is it like in Bob reference
frame if the distance to Alice in your
reference frame at rest is fixed and Bob
is going faster and faster what does Bob
say about
Alice well she's not so much going the
opposite way is she's just getting Lo
she's getting separated farther and
farther because of
Lorent
contraction so Bob
says oh my goodness Alice is getting
farther and farther away from me even
though the observers at rest say that uh
that Alice is a fixed distance
away she can't get closer because she
can't get past this light cone she can't
get up to the speed she can't go faster
than the speed of
light right So eventually from Bob's
point of view here Alice just drags
further and further and further behind
and if it happens not to be Alice Bob
but happens to be Alice's head and
Alice's feet then Alice's feet are just
stretched stretched stretched away from
her until
uh uh bad things happen until they
break so once Alice's feet are behind
the Horizon she has two Alternatives
fall in with them no problem nothing
unusual or stay out of the black hole
and uh she will be uh
defeated defeated oh that was
good now so
far we haven't discussed anything about
the singularity of the black
hole so let's start to talk about the
singularity of the black hole where is
it on this chart here where is it on
this diagram let's clean up the diagram
again let's get rid of the head and the
foot and let's come back to the Schwartz
Shield metric let's rewrite the Schwartz
Shield
metric dt^ 2 * 1 - 2 mg /
r with a minus sign and with a plus sign
1/ 1 - 2 mg
/
R the r s and then there's another term
R for the uh for the angular coordinates
let's suppress that not worry about
it the term which has the negative sign
is always time you always recognize time
or the Tim like
variables by a minus sign in front of
their
metric you recognize the space likee
variable
ordinary Space by a positive sign in the
metric but something happens when R
crosses 2 mg when R is greater than 2 mg
this is positive 2 mg over R is small
one minus a small number is positive but
when R gets smaller than 2 mg suddenly
the sign changes here the sign also
changes here it means that somehow R is
becoming a Tim like variable and T is
becoming a space-like variable that this
does not mean that anything dramat
doesn't mean space turns into time
behind the black hole
Horizon this is a feature of a peculiar
set of
coordinates when you go past the Horizon
the coordinates interchange what's
happening here is something like this if
you were to move in along a surface of
constant time toward the horizon
you would get to the
Horizon you would R would be decreasing
are decreasing decreasing decreasing
until it gets to 2
mg and then where does it go from there
then suddenly when R gets past the
Horizon it becomes a Tim likee
coordinate R goes up that way
what about if Omega is a little bigger
or t is a little bigger so we come in
also to the Horizon this is Omega equals
0 this is Omega equal 1 one unit of time
later we also come in and we hit this
point here and then these coordinates
these Schwarz Shield coordinates which
are peculiar coordinates suddenly make
another turn and go off here
so they're funny coordinates there's
nothing special happening over here it's
just a choice of coordinates that you've
used where on one side of the Horizon R
is a Tim like a space-like variable on
the other side of the Horizon it's a
time like variable and vice versa time
turns into space space turns into time
but nothing really is happening at this
point it's just an ordinary generic
point of uh SpaceTime
okay now let's go to where the
singularity lies The Singularity is at R
equals zero that's a nasty place there's
something very dramatic happening there
tidal forces become infinite curvature
becomes
infinite all hell breaks loose at the
singularity that's R equals
z well as we start coming in we go to R
equals 2 mg that's not zero
then we continue
along the r axis think of it as the r
AIS but the r axis makes a right angle
turn until we get to r equal 0 and
that's over here this is r equal
0 we do the same thing on another curve
and we come to r equal 0 over here if we
connect all the points that correspond
to R equals 0 together it looks like
this it looks like a hyperbola it is a h
hyperbola that hyperbola is a
singularity let's draw it having a nasty
Wicked points because it's highly curved
and very
unpleasant you sort of thought
originally that the singularity was a
place a place means a place is a a
Vertical World line but it's not a place
it's a Time
moving along here the singularity occurs
after a certain amount of time not
really a place it's a kind of pine
there's the
singularity that's the nasty place okay
let's um let's think about now poor
Alice
who has fallen behind the Horizon here
she's over
here where does she go next she wants to
escape the terrible fate of falling into
The
Singularity she can try to get
out or she can try to go that way either
way she cannot Escape there's no way
that she can without ex without
exceeding the speed of light she cannot
Escape the Fate of falling into the
singularity so that's another property
once you pass the Horizon that's it you
have no chance but to fall into the
singularity not only can't you
communicate to the outside but you're
doomed you're doomed by The
Singularity and that does one more
feature of the black
hole now the
mathematics of this
metric it's now we come to a real
curiosity but it's a mathematical
artifact which we're going to find
doesn't really mean anything physical
but still is a mathematical
artifact this geometry here
is the same if you turn time to minus
time in fact these coefficients here
don't depend on time
altogether and what happens to dt^ 2 if
we take time to minus
time it stays the same this metric here
is what a physicist would call time
reversal invariant it looks the same
going forward as going
backward well well that's a little bit
peculiar because you can see over
here that sort of forward in time
there's a
singularity what it
implies is that there must be a
singularity also in the past and if you
study this metric in its mathematical
detail you'll find out that what it
really represents is a Time symmetric
situation with a singularity in the
past and a singularity in the future
now Alice doesn't have to worry about
the singularity in the past there's no
way she can get back to the past you
can't get back to the past she has to
worry about the singularity in the
future okay she's going to fall into the
uh into the singularity over here but
let's just uh think of Alice's history
for a moment incidentally the meaning of
saying that something is time reversal
invariant is the same as saying that a
particular history if you were to run it
backward if you are watching watching
the events taking place and you were to
run them backward meaning to say you
would to take a film of them and run the
film backward that the backward film
would also be a
possible history which makes sense as a
solution of the equations of the theory
that's what it means for something to be
time
reversible the equations of general
relativity are completely time revers
ible so anything that can happen forward
can also happen backward so let's think
about what that
means here's a history Alice jumps into
the black hole and winds up on the
singularity there as she passes The
Horizon Bob loses track of her can't see
her well if that's a possible history
then we should be able to fold it
over and say there's another possible
solution solution of the equations in
which Alice is created at the
singularity and jumps out of the black
hole well there's Bob looking back at
the black
hole oh she has no trouble going this
way no trouble at
all she can't cross out from here
well the uh the time reverse of that has
nothing to do with her ability to get
out of this this is called a past
Horizon Alice has no trouble at all
getting out of the past
Horizon it's simply the time reversal of
the statement that Alice had no trouble
falling into the
Horizon the time reverse of passing out
here the Horizon time reverse of passing
in is passing out so if she can pass
into the Horizon in the future she can
pass out of the past Horizon in the
past what does Bob
see Bob looks back and sees something
silly he sees a Alice ejected out of
this black
hole that's silly of course right I mean
that that's uh that's nonsense right so
there's something wrong with this
picture we're going to find out what it
is
h no no no no no no yes here's Bob over
here he looks back he actually seems to
be able to see the singularity that's in
itself a little bit annoying he looks
back and he sees the singularity oh boy
and then he suddenly sees Alice jump out
from the
singularity what what ises that called
anybody know what that's called this
nonsensical uh configuration fiction
fiction yes it
is well the first thing is yes it is
possible is it likely no it's unlikely
this is called a white
hole a white hole this is what a white
hole is now white holes don't exist they
don't really make sense doesn't Bob also
have a a history going in reverse at
this point no Bob is Bob is out here
he's just doing what he ordinarily does
this is not this is this is fictional
this is not something that makes a lot
of sense um it's about as likely as
um uh you uh well what's a good
example you evaporate water from a
puddle into a uh inter
space
um instead you see uh water
materializing from space well this this
can happen can't it it's called uh just
a condensation I better I better be I
better be careful all
right a bomb explodes a bomb explodes
and uh sends garbage all over the place
right that's a possible history of let's
say Newton's equations for a bunch of
particles
where you start with a
bomb you know one of these old fashion
bombs that Bolsheviks carried
around with a fuse
and like my grandfather would have had
I'm
sure and uh you wait a little while boom
and stuff gets scattered all over the
place you'd be pretty damn surprised to
see a bunch of stuff flying inward
reassembling the bomb and doing it very
delicately so that eventually it just
had a little bit of a flame at the end
of the that that doesn't happen right
not going to happen but wait a minute
it's a possible solution of the equation
of the of Newton's Theory Newton's
theory is completely time
reversible okay so what's wrong both are
possible but we know very well that one
of them is not
possible okay what uh just to throw
words uh doesn't
help yeah it's entropy and it's
uh one of them is clearly extremely
unlikely
the other is rather likely they're both
possible with the inverse process where
stuff comes
in and creates the
bomb all you would have to do is move
one molecule a tiny tiny fraction of the
of molecular distance in the incident
state to completely undo the ability to
uh to create the bomb it's extreme
extremely unstable the backward
trajectory it's sort of like imagine I
have a very high mountain that comes to
a point it's very easy to roll a ball
off the top starting at
rest just give it that tiniest little
kick where will it go it'll fall down
the mountain the probability that it
will fall down the mountain is extremely
high the reverse trajectory is possible
throwing the ball up to and just getting
up to the top but extremely unlikely the
tiniest little bit of error and you wind
up missing the top another example
everybody here uh play pool when they
were kids Billiards you
know yeah of course you did uh you start
with all the billiard balls all the uh
the the balls racked up in a triangle
perfect triangle
how many of them are
there
15 right and you take a c ball you give
it a good hard shot and they go
scattering all over the place high
probability that they'll just scatter
all over the place it would be rather
amazing to see 15 billiard balls even if
we didn't worry about friction on the on
the table it would be rather amazing to
see 15 billiard balls come together and
form a perfect triangle with a Q ball
going out that way
pretty unlikely right but both of them
are solutions of the same equations so
both are possible from the point of view
of the equations but the difference is
that if you started those 15 16 balls in
a configuration which was
just perfect so that they reassembled
into the
triangle and then the tiniest little
error you would miss the triangle
completely and all you would make would
be a table full of billiard balls going
in random directions yes but also isn't
it just as unlikely that you would have
precisely the same thing uh going the
other way uh every time you did it yes
in know each each of these is equally
unlikely yes yes that's that that is
correct but uh you know if you were just
to say I'm not I'm I'm watching this
thing and what I see is billiard balls
scattered all over the place yeah if you
did it over and over and over again you
would get more or less the same pattern
every time billiard balls scattered all
over the place and unless you were
following the billiard balls carefully
you wouldn't notice there was a
particular uh differences but you would
notice if the billiard balls came
together and formed a triangle so yes
you're right I mean any given I think
your point is any given configuration is
very unlikely right all right that's
where entropy comes in and uh but what
Bob is seeing here and we're ultimately
going to understand this in terms the
entropy of the black
hole but what Bob is seeing here what we
Now understand is he's seeing one of
these very very unlikely processes not
an impossible process but unlikely where
a black hole just sitting there suddenly
spurts out a uh a full-fledged version
of uh Alice very unlikely but not
unlikely that Alice falls into the black
hole so it it really is very very much
the same thing we're going to find out
that this is one of the aspects of black
holes that has to do with their entropy
we've already discovered black holes
have
entropy
uh they're in thermal equilibrium they
have thermal
properties you could say the same thing
about a pot of hot water what's the
likelihood that if you drop an ice cube
into a pot of hot water that it will
form a melted uh configuration with the
water just getting a little more water
in it and filling up the pot a little
more very high right what's the
probability to sit and wait and watch
that pot that an ice cube will get
ejected out of
it but both of them satisfy the same
equations both of quantum mechanics and
classical mechanics so in that sense
they are both uh they are both possible
the same thing going on here the Horizon
of the black hole has entropy just like
the pot of water hidden information
very rarely very rarely will the entropy
of the black hole of the pot of water
assemble itself into an ice cube same
thing here very rarely will the garbage
and the Horizon of the black hole
assemble itself into ejecting uh
Alice is that probability all quantum
mechanical probability or is it a
something it could be both It's a
combination of quantum mechanical and
thermal thermal fluctuations and uh
quantum mechanical fluctuations both are
uh are
there but um in the case of the hot
water of course it's mostly
thermal
right
okay uh let's take a five minute break
and then we're going to talk about
Penrose diagrams and we're going to talk
about actually making black
holes uh how you actually make a black
hole and why half of this Di diagram
namely the bottom half is completely
unphysical it's not something you ever
really have to worry about the bottom
half which is the peculiar half of the
white
hole Yeah Michael asked me a question
and I realized in the when he asked the
question that I was using a bit of
jargon so let me just clarify the
jargon uh I used I told you that row was
proper distance from The Horizon the
jargon there was proper
distance let me just uh remind
you what proper distance means it is a
piece of jargon it's similar to proper
time what is proper time along a
observer's trajectory
measure it measures wristwatch time
right but it's wristwatch time along
among a curve right all right now we
have over here
Bob and let's take Bob right at time
equals
zero it draws the straightest path he
can to the
Horizon in this case a straight line
what does it mean to say that this is a
given proper distance away from the
Horizon yeah yeah it's the distance
measured by real yard sticks or meter
sticks in this uh in this uh room we
don't allow yard sticks in this room we
allow meter sticks me distance measured
with honest meter
sticks okay that's all that's all it
means uh that to say
now little r where is it little r up
there I think I've erased it little r
over here does not measure proper
distance it's just a mathematical
coordinate which is not proper distance
it doesn't measure real meter sticks
distance row is the thing that measures
real meter sticks so I apologize for
jargon but uh sometimes I
forget
okay now let's talk about Penrose
diagrams Penrose diagrams are great they
really are the way to understand all
kinds of things in general
relativity and they're easy they're easy
to think about easy to
draw a little bit difficult to actually
work out in detail but we don't need to
work them out in
detail let's draw SpaceTime on the
Blackboard in in
particular let's draw just ordinary flat
SpaceTime on the Blackboard well we
don't have enough dimensions on the
Blackboard to draw for dimensional space
time so let's pick out two coordinates
one will be time and the other will be
distance from the origin now this is
ordinary flat space time so it could be
T and
row right time runs vertically
upward
T and row is just distance from the
origin
here so it runs sort of this way here's
the row axis
we can make a grid out of this by
chomping up the time axis into intervals
and then extrapolating them
horizontally and we can make a vertical
grid so the first point here is row
equals Zer incidentally nothing to the
left because by definition row is always
positive it's the proper distance from
the it's a sort of polar coordinate uh
kind of uh coordinate so it's always
positive and here it is here's all of
SpaceTime this is row = 0 along here Row
= 1 Row = 2 Row = 3 here's t = 0 t = 1
tal minus1 time can get Negative in this
picture and this is the history of the
whole
universe how about light waves let's
take a light wave that comes in from the
remote past comes
in hits the origin what happens after it
hits the
origin it just goes back out it's not
really bouncing off anything it's just
here's the origin my fist is the origin
it just goes right through the origin
but in polar coordinates it comes in and
goes
out so there's a light wave that comes
in and goes out a later light wave might
come in later and bounce out and so
forth
again that's the history of the world on
a small Blackboard but it's not the
history of the whole world is the
Blackboard isn't big enough to describe
the whole world the whole world meaning
all infinite distances out to infinity
and all infinite times from minus
infinity to plus
infinity so
what relativists
do is they make coordinate
Transformations that's what relativity
is all about it's about coordinate
Transformations but in particular
coordinate Transformations which take
the whole expanse of space and time and
simply squash it by coordinate
transformation onto a finite region of
the
Blackboard what you get is called a
Penrose
diagram there's a rule and the rule is
that however you draw the Penrose
diagram basically only two rules the
first thing is use coordinat that gets
the whole thing onto the finite
Blackboard squish it and squash it until
you get the whole thing on the
Blackboard but subject to the rule that
light rays radially going light rays
always move at 45 degree
angles this can be done for a very large
variety of
geometries that you can squish it down
squish it down in such a way that the
light rays continue to move at
45° the result is called Penrose diagram
and don't worry about the mathematics of
how you derive the particular Penrose
diagram just learn to read them because
they're easy to read here's what it
looks like here's what the Penrose
diagram of flat space looks like there's
the time axis but it doesn't go from
minus infinity to plus infinity well it
does but we draw the whole
thing between some point in the past and
some point in the future and that's the
whole time
axis the space axis
also goes out to some point that's
really R equals infinity or row equals
infinity but we squash it in and the
rest of it is just a triangle in
here there it
is all right let's see if we can take
this
grid and replot it on
here
start over here and work your way
outward that's T equals z and work your
way
outward here's row equal 1 here's row
equal 2 row equal 3 but we've got to
crowd an infinite number of them into
here so they're going to crowd up like
that likewise let's take
time time one and they're going to crowd
up as we go up here and likewise down
here let's try drawing this
grid Tim like lines vertical Tim like
lines
all go up to time Infinity that's up
here that's time Infinity up here so all
these vertical lines look like
this more and more and more of them out
here what about the horizontal lines
they all go out to row equals infinity
that's all over here it's all been
squished or smushed into a point over
there it looks like this
curved okay what about light rays in
particular light rays that are aimed
from far away toward the origin light
rays come
in
from first of all they move on 45 degree
lines and the incoming light Ray would
look like
that that would be the image
in this diagram of the light Ray which
came in like this it bounces off the
origin and goes back
out you could have earlier light
rays that came in earlier and bounce
back
earlier all light rays all incoming
light rays originate on this side of the
triangle now that's really way way out
at Infinity way down here all outgoing
light
rays pass out of the diagram up here
that's just ASM totically far away in
that direction what about all timik
lines timik lines are these observers
for example these people who are
standing still they might be moving a
little bit they all wind up up here
where do they come from they come from
here if you walk out you can't walk out
uh but if you imagined moving outward
along one of these timelines here to
larger and larger row it would
eventually get over to here this diagram
and that diagram are the same diagram
this one has just been smoed or squished
or whatever your favorite word is so
that it can all be drawn on the
Blackboard but subject to the constraint
that the speed of light stays uh the
light rays move at 45 degree angles
this is called a Penrose diagram this is
the simplest Penrose diagram and that's
all it
is uh what else is there to say about
this particular pen yeah are those light
lines squish to meet the corners of each
of those squares as it goes through is
that light line curved or is it
always um as it passes through each of
those squares yeah is it supposed to be
passing through the the corners of each
one as it goes through so it would
slightly curve as it goes through the
ground I suppose it would be if it were
uh I suppose it would be if we drew it
accurately um yeah if we drew it
accurately it would be yeah this is true
since it's passing through the corners
here right they all end up at 90° to
that or to that outside
boundary what about a light Ray that uh
was pointed not right at the origin but
missed the
origin how would you draw that well we
could we you could come back here first
and draw it here you still have to be
45° so it just intersect the higher
lower Point wouldn't it no no no it
misses the origin it never gets to the
origin so it comes in when it's very
very far away it looks like it's aimed
straight toward the origin so it looks
it follows this route here but it
doesn't quite get to the origin it comes
into a distance of closest approach and
then goes back out so in fact it would
look like this
it gets to a distance of closest
approach and then goes back out but of
course there's angles involved it
doesn't come out in the same in the same
direction that it came in in but on this
diagram uh all right so same thing here
a light
Ray that misses the
origin just simply misses it it never
quite gets to it it gets to a distance
of closest approach over here and then
goes back out but then it's not going at
45° yeah I said radial light rays are
drawn at
45° radial light rays ones which are
aimed
radially right ones which are not radial
you have to worry about specially you
have to take that into account okay
these different places these different
um extreme limits of the Penrose
diagrams have names of course this is
just a Time axis this one up here is
called future Tim like
Infinity this and it's usually just
called
t+ or tals Infinity you know how about
just tals Infinity this one down here is
called tal minus
infinity time like past Infinity time
like future Infinity what would you call
this
one space like Infinity so this is row
equals infinity over here
what about these got a name for
those they're the places where light
rays come in from they're called light
like Infinity this one's called past
light like Infinity this one's called
future light like infinity and for
reasons that I have no idea this was
originally labeled I I minus minus for
past and
I for the
future it was always labeled with a
script by and known as scry scry minus
and scry plus not my not my notation so
I don't have to apologize for
it um good so that's the Penrose diagram
of flat
SpaceTime what about a black hole what
does a black hole look like so to get to
get to a black hole let's
redraw the diagram that we had
earlier and then try to see what it
would look like if we did some smushing
and
squishing to squeeze it onto the
Blackboard okay here's what we
saw we saw way out here was space like
Infinity way that's way out the large
distances from the black
hole you time coordinates like
that here was the singularity over
here there was also a past Singularity
over
here and we never discussed what was on
this side we never discussed what was on
this side I I hesitated to tell you what
was down here but I eventually did right
what's on this side nothing of physical
interest but nevertheless the
mathematics of the what Shield
metric contains all of this it contains
an outside world over here and another
outside world over here this outside
world is not the same as this outside
world over here you can't get a message
from here to here but the mathematics of
Schwarz Shield has both of these we're
going to find that half of this is
really quite meaningless but for the
moment this is what we found the metric
looked like this is what the geometry
looked like so let's ask what happens if
we squish
this we're going to do the same kind of
squeezing to get everything onto the
finite plane and I'm just going to draw
it for you I'll show you what it looks
like you'll recogn I think you'll
recognize it pretty
fast let's see I need some guidelines to
do it
with and I'll show you how to read it in
a minute
okay okay let's start out here at R
equals
infinity that's like R equals infinity
or row equals infinity that's like way
out here where do you think it ought to
go way out
here
okay this Horizon over here the bifet
Horizon is right at the center over
here if I start at the Horizon and go
out to Infinity I can go this way but I
can also go along this
line This is Omega equals 0 this is
Omega equal 1 where is that on here and
and notice you in either case you wind
up sort of in the same place same place
sort of you wind up going out to Ral
Infinity Ral Infinity is all been
smushed down to here so where do you go
you go out to
here likewise from
here that's the sequence of different
time now let's look at different radial
distances from the black hole different
radial distances I'm going to change
color different radial
distances
all these are observers if you like who
are stationary outside the black hole
they go up to time Infinity over here
and they look like
this
okay so this guy is 200 mil from the
black hole I don't know this one's 500
mil from the black hole that's 1,000 mil
from the black hole that's 10,000 miles
from the black hole and so
forth this on over here
is hovering right above the
Horizon and in fact because he's trying
to hover above the Horizon he must be
accelerated to hover above the Horizon
takes some rockets that are going to
keep him from falling through so that's
him over
here the other side is a perfect
reflection of this
side and this diamond here that's the
outside of the black hole that's the
outside of the the black hole that's
where Bob lives he lives out here and if
he doesn't want to cross the Horizon
where's the
Horizon that's
this well this is the bifurcate Horizon
this is sort of the point of no return
over here what is
this that's the singularity that's the
image of the singularity over here so
here we go here's the
singularity what's this one
that's the past Singularity one was down
there past
Singularity future Singularity past
Singularity this is either r or row
equals
infinity either way how about light rays
which come
in they come in from
here but now they don't bounce off the
origin what happens to them if they're
radially inward
what
happens do they bounce off and go back
out no they fall into the black
hole they pass through here and where do
they wind
up the
singularity okay there are light rays
which go out to
Infinity of course they could have been
created by somebody here one of these
people here could have had a flashlight
and send a light Ray out but there are
also mathematical light rays which begin
on the past Singularity and get radiated
out this is called T equals
infinity and it's the analog of the
point up here this is called tal minus
infinity this is called R equals
infinity this is
called past light like Infinity this is
called future light like
Infinity okay and that's it that's the
black hole that's the schw shield black
hole in a nutshell drawn all of
SpaceTime drawn on a finite piece of a
plane radially moving light rays always
45° from this picture you can see a lot
of what
the of the properties of black holes
well we've talked about them already
we've talked about what happens when
Alice Falls in when Bob stays outside
here's Bob
here's Alice except here Alice is a
photon but the fallace was moving more
slowly but same thing would happen and
once you cross into this triangle here
you're doomed you have no choice but to
go to the
singularity now what is this region out
here that seems like a second
world it looks like the black hole this
is the source of a lot of Science
Fiction it looks like the there are two
worlds connected together by a black
hole H Wormhole a wormhole right a
wormhole however it's not possible to go
from this world to this
world because even a light Ray once it
passed this Horizon would wind up over
here so they're completely out of
communication with each
other nobody on this side can signal
anybody on this side so from the point
of view of anybody in this diamond here
this doesn't
exist well that's a little bit glib
isn't it to say it just doesn't exist in
fact the
real story is a little bit different the
real story has to do with the way black
holes are made in
nature this diagram doesn't tell you how
this black hole was made this black hole
was sort of always there from the remot
from the remote past to the remote
future The schwat Shield metric was
there so it's a black hole which is
eternal black holes are not Eternal
they're made they're made by collapsing
Stars so the next question that we want
to understand is how is a black hole
made now a black hole before there's a
black hole it's not completely empty
space stuff was coming in we can imagine
Let's uh let's take an imaginary
scenario some particles come in from
very far away they might even be
photons when enough photons come in a
region of
space photons have energy therefore they
have mass enough photons and mass and
therefore they gravitate if you can get
enough Photon energy into a region of
space you can make a black
hole so we can start with not with
nothing but but with just a very diffuse
cloud of photons coming in from far away
that's practically empty space looks a
lot like empty space where's the diagram
that represents empty space that's here
that's empty
space no black hole
just plain empty space Maybe with some
photons coming
in after the photons come in if they
make a black hole then later what we
should see is the black hole the
question is how do you put these
together how do you put this together in
the past with this in the future to
represent the assembling of a black hole
so we want to go through that we want to
spend a little bit of time assembling a
black hole to do so I have to tell you a
theorem I think the theorem will do for
tonight and we'll go through the
construction next time
but it's called
in Newtonian physics it's called
Newton's theorem in general relativity
it's called birkoff's theorem and it's a
very simple fact about Newtonian gravity
or about general relativity it's easy to
understand hard to
prove let's begin with Newton's theorem
Newton proved this uh it's a theorem
about one over R SAR
forces one over R squ forces can uh such
as the kulum force in electromagnetism
or the Newtonian force of gravity 1/ R 2
forces can be described by lines of
force I'll just remind you about lines
of
force here's your mass let's say it's a
point mass and imagine lines of force
coming out of it the lines of force
could also be flow lines of a
fluid coming out of a
uh coming out of a source at the origin
it could be two-dimensional with fluid
spreading out over two Dimensions or it
could be uh threedimensional Source over
here where fluid flows away from the
source and you draw lines of force the
lines of Force begin on the charged
particle or the massive object and just
just go out and they don't end they
don't end of course unless there's
another Mass someplace or another charge
someplace but let's say there's just one
Mass that's uh that's the uh and what's
the rule for the either electric field
or the gravitational field the rule is
at any
point the gravitational field oh I think
I will draw the gravitational lines
pointing inward why is
that yeah because gravity attracts
so it's pulling on
things so the rule is at any point the
force do the force on a test object
points along the direction of the line
of force that passes through that point
and what about the magnitude of the
force the magnitude of the gravitational
field it's proportional to the density
of the lines if you think of if space is
being filled up with a uh
a network of lines that The Closer they
are together the stronger the force all
right so lines of force uh it's an
imaginary mathematical construction you
fill up space with these lines of force
or lines of flow of a fluid that is
everything that uh that you can say
about the Newtonian field gravitational
field of a point object if you put two
point objects together then you just add
the fields which is exactly the same as
saying I have two sources a fluid in
this case I guess this would be a sync
of fluid because the fluid is flowing in
you have two sinks of fluid the fluid is
being pulled in and so you have two
sources and you simply sum the field of
both of them which means you study the
flu the the fluid flow of the two
sources jux
opposed all right if you work out that
you figure out the uh the field of an
arbitrary distribution of masses now
the Newton theorem is the following it
says if I take a spherically symmetric
distribution of mass and I'm going to
take a very simple case I'm going to
take a
shell the theorem is more General than
I'm I'm going to say but I'm going to
take a shell a shell a thin
shell spherically symmetric of
mass here it
is you can think of every point on that
shell as producing
fluid if you look on the inside of the
shell there is no flow how could there
be which way would the flow flow if you
were inside the shell well you might say
it flows radially by symmetry it would
flow radially but if there was flow
inside the shell where would it
go there's no mass at the
center I'm assuming all of the mass is
on the shell there's no place for the
fluid to
go so if there's no mass at the center
there can't be any radial flow there
can't be any flow at all so the interior
of a shell of sources of fluid has no
flow at all in it which is another way
of saying there's no gravitational field
at all inside a spherical shell like
this what about the
outside the
outside has a flow which is radially
outward the lines of force look exactly
as if they had emanated from the point
at the
center and the total amount of flow is
whatever the total amount of flow coming
out of the shell is in the language of
gravitation what it says is the
gravitational field of a shell of mass m
outside the shell is absolutely
identical to a gravitational field of a
Point Mass at the
center but inside the shell there's no
gravitational field at all so inside the
shell exactly the same as empty
space okay outside the shell exactly the
same as the point
Mass there's a general relativity
version of
this uh incidentally let me say
something else this is true even if the
shell is time dependent for example as
long as the total amount of fluid coming
out of it is is uh is
conserved if the shell were to change
size in a way that did not change the
total amount of fluid coming out of it
with time it would still be true at any
given
instant the gravitational field inside
the shell would be that of empty space
and the gravitational field outside
would look exactly like the point Mass
it would just be the place where you go
from outside to inside which would
change with time so in particular if you
had a Time dependent shell of mass which
was
Contracting with a mass staying
fixed then outside it point you would
see the point Mass gravitational field
inside you would see nothing only the
boundary between the two regions would
change with time the same exact thing is
true in general relativity almost the
same thing close not quite but close all
right so let me tell you what is called
burkov
theorem and then the next time we will
combine burkov theorem with these two
diagrams and put together the theory of
how a black hole is
formed
okay so get burov theorem remember it
all right what does it say it says if
you have a spherically symmetric
distribution of
mass what do you see inside the
spherically symmetric distribution of
mass exactly what you would see if there
was no mass at all flat SpaceTime empty
space
flat uh manowski whatever you want to
call it just the solution of gravitate
of Einstein's theory with absolutely
nothing there just good old empty space
inside what about on the outside what do
you
say you see a Newtonian gravitational
field no not quite what do you think you
see on the
outside it's it's spherical Mass but
what's the gravitational field on the
outside Schwarz shield in other words
the metric on the inside is exactly that
of flat space and the metric on the
outside is exactly that of the Schwarz
Shield black hole we won't well we can
write it on the inside we have good old
the
t^2 minus the x s the y^ S the z^2 and
on the outside we have uh schwar Shield
I'm not going to write
it I think I could have written the
metric faster than I could have written
Schwarz Shield
uh
right in other words we piece together
two things both of which we know very
well connected together by a shell how
about the mass of the Schwarz Shield
solution Schwarz Shield solution has a
mass associated with
it it's just the mass of the total shell
does the mass of the shell change with
time even if it moves even if the shell
contracts does the total mass of the
shell change with time why
not well supposing I tell you supposing
I just mutter the words E equals mc²
conservation of energy right the mass
the total mass of that shell even if the
shell and can the shell change of course
the shell can change uh you build
yourself a shell but the shell isn't
strong enough to maintain itself against
the gravitational field what happens it
starts to collapse as it collapses the
mass doesn't
change but the radius of it changes what
was inside was just good old flat space
What was side was schwat shield and the
boundary between the two behaviors might
change with time so what we're going to
do next time is we're going to take the
flat space Solution that's the
inside and Patch it together with the
outside which is the SWAT Shi solution
I'll show you how to do that and in that
way we will learn in a very simple
example how a black hole is formed we'll
find that half of this diagram doesn't
mean anything but we'll come to it next
time so formation of a black hole next
time
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu